好的，
Alright,
欢迎学习 6.S081 操作系统，
welcome to 6.S081 operating systems,
我是 Robert ，将和 Frans 一起执教，
I'm Robert I'll be Co lecturing with Frans
David 和 Nicolass 作为助教。
and David and Nicolass of the TAs.
在 zoom 讲座的的时候，
So, please during the zoom lecturers,
随时可以提问，
ask questions,
你可以讲话打断我，
you can either interrupt me by audio
或者在聊天窗口中输入一些东西。
or enter something into the chat window,
我们会有一名工作人员查看并替你提问。
one of the staff will see and ask questions for you.
顺便说一下，我们会录下这些讲座，
By the way, we'll be recording these lectures
然后把录像开放出来，
and then we'll post recordings later,
这样你们可以复习，
so you can review them
或者对于来不了的人
or for people who can't make this time
他们仍然可以看到讲座。
so they can nevertheless see lectures.
好的，首先我想列出一些课程目标，
Alright, I want to start by laying out some of the goals of the course,
第一个目标是，
So, number one is to,
理解操作系统的设计和实现。
understand the design and implementation of operating systems.
是的，设计是一种高层次的结构，
Yeah, design is sort of high level structure
而实现是实际中代码真正的样子，
and implementation is really about what the code looks like,
我们将做这两个方面花费大量的时间。
and we'll be spending a lot of time with both.
为了更深入地理解这是怎么运行的，
And in the interest of getting deep understanding of what's going on,
你经通过一个小型操作系统获得实践经验，
you'll get hands-on experience with a small, a small operating system,
就是我们的 xv6 操作系统。
the xv6 operating system.
而且除了查看现有的操作系统，
And in addition to actually looking at an existing operating system,
你还可以从实验中获得一下经验，
you'll be in the labs get a bunch of experience,
扩展操作系统，改进操作系统，
extending the operating system modifying improving its behavior
编写使用操作系统接口的系统软件，
and writing system software that it uses the operating system interfaces,
在运行应用程序时。
[if it works an application].
所以，这是你们在课程中要做的，
So, this is what you're going to be doing in the course.
在课程中，我们对操作系统
We're also interested in what the purpose of the operating system
本身的作用也很感兴趣。
itself is as well as the course.
所以，我有一系列的东西，
So for that, I have a sort of list of a couple of things
你知道，有很多操作系统，
which you know there's lots of operating system,
不同的操作系统，
different operating systems out there,
它们通常有一个共同的目标。
they typically have a common set of purposes.
其中之一就是对硬件的抽象，
One of them is to abstract the hardware,
通常从买一台计算机开始，
that is what you're given typically as a starting point is you buy a computer,
计算机包括 CPU 和内存，
a computer has a CPU and memory,
但这是一个非常低的层级。
but that's a very low level.
一系列的资源，
A set of resources,
拥有更高级别的接口和抽象是非常棒的，
it's fantastic to have a much higher level interfaces and abstractions
应用程序可以使用它们，
that applications can use,
比如为了方便和可移植性而产生的进程或文件系统。
such as processes or file systems both for convenience and for portability.
操作系统的另一个非常重要的目标是
Another very important task of an operating system is
在许多应用程序中复用硬件。
to multiplex the hardware among many applications.
你可能运行文本编辑器，编译器，
You might be running a text editor, and a compiler,
或者多个不同的数据库服务器，
or maybe a multiple different database servers
或者其他什么东西，
or something on your operating system,
能够使用操作系统
it's fantastic to be able to have the operating system
同时运行它们是很棒的，
run both of them at the same time
而且所有同时运行的事情不会相互干扰。
or all the things are going on at the same time without having them interfere.
这通常叫做多路复用，
That's often called multiplexing,
因为操作系统上
because there may be a lot of things
可能同时发生很多事情，
happening in the operating system at the same time,
它们必须不会相互干扰，
it's critical that they not interfere unintentionally,
即使有 bug 存在，
even if they have bugs
这也就是所谓的隔离性。
and that's a task is called isolation.
它的主要思想是，不同的活动不应该互相干涉，
The idea that, different activities should not be allowed to interfere,
另一方面，
on the other hand,
不同的活动可以需要干涉，
there are times when different activities would like to interfere,
需要干涉来交互或协作，
would like to interact or cooperate,
比如，如果我使用编辑器创建了一个文件，
so for example if I create a file with a text editor,
我希望编译器可以读取该文件，
and I'd like my compiler to read the file
我们肯定希望允许这样的的共享。
and we definitely want to allow that kind of sharing.
所有我们希望这种用户想要的共享。
So we wanna allow sharing [], sort of what the user has in mind.
但是在很多情况下，用户不想分享，
But in many circumstances, the user doesn't want sharing,
可能你登录到类似 Athena 的分时服务器，
maybe you're logged into a time sharing machine like Athena,
你肯定不希望别人读取你的文件，
and you don't want other people to read your files,
所以我们需要，想分享的的时候分享，
so we also need as well sharing we want to,
不想分享的时候不分享。
not share when we don't want to.
我们可以称其为安全系统或权限系统，
Which we could call security or a permission system,
即一个访问控制系统。
an access control system.
人们看中操作系统的另一个原因是，
Another thing that people value in operating systems is
如果你为一台计算机的硬件上花了很多钱，
if you spend a lot of money on the hardware on a computer,
你希望应用程序能够获得
you'd like your application to be able to get
硬件提供的全部性能。
a sort of full performance that a hardware ought to be able to provide.
而且，很多都是应用编程。
And, a lot of that is just application programming.
但是，不可避免的，
But, inevitably, unfortunately, some of it is
操作系统必须确保
the operating system has to make sure that
它提供的任何服务
whatever services it provides
都不会阻碍应用程序获得高性能，
don't get in the way of applications getting high performance,
所以你希望至少不要阻碍，
so you want to at least not get in the way
甚至可以帮助应用程序获得良好的性能。
and maybe even help applications achieve good performance.
最后，大多数操作系统
Finally, with most operating systems
必须支持很多不同的应用程序，
have to support a wide range of different applications,
可能是笔记本电脑运行编辑器，
maybe it's a laptop running a text editor,
可能是运行游戏，
maybe it's running games,
也可能操作系统需要支持
maybe your operating system needs to
数据库服务或云计算，
support database servers or cloud computation,
通常因为操作系统的设计和构建成本很高，
and usually because operating systems are quite expensive to design and build,
所以人们使用相同的操作系统来执行许多不同的任务，
people use the same operating systems for many different tasks,
比如 Linux ，
like Linux,
我相信大多数人都运行一个（操作系统），
for example which I'm sure many of you are running a,
在我提到的所有情况下，
is used in all of the situations I mentioned,
所以相同的操作系统必须能够支持，
so the same operating system really has to be able to support
一系列非常不同的用途。
a range of often quite different uses.
所以我们希望能够，
So we're hoping to be able to support
同时支持所有这些不同的目标。
sort of all these different goals simultaneously.
我们将在课程中听到更多关于这些的信息。
And we'll hear more about all of them during the course.
好的，对于操作系统，
Alright, operating systems,
几十年来人们总结出一套设计思想，
a lot of people worked out a set of design ideas over the decades
在组织事情方面运行良好，
have worked pretty well sort of ways of organizing things,
我来给你们展示一下这种经典设计。
I'm going to lay out for you this sort of classic.
也是这门课的标准组织方式，
A organization sort of standard deal for for this course,
实际上在很多操作系统上都是很常见的，
and is actually quite common around for many operate systems,
所以这是一种操作系统的内部组织方式，
so this is sort of OS internal organization,
我想用这个方框来表示计算机，
or the way I think about it is in terms of a box for the computer,
计算机包含许多硬件，
the computer sort of comes with a bunch of hardware resources,
我把它们放在下面，
which I'll put at the bottom,
有 CPU 、 内存、用来存储的磁盘，可能还有网络接口，
maybe their CPU and ram, disk for storage and maybe a network interface,
这些硬件是最下面一层。
this sort of hardware that's the lowest layer.
而在顶部，你想要运行各种应用程序，
So at the top you want to run various applications,
或许是一个文本编辑器，这里我使用 vi 来表示，
maybe a text editor I have use VI as a text editor,
也可能是运行 C 编译器 CC ，
if you're going to run a C compiler CC,
也可以运行很多我们今天会讨论的其他东西，
you know if you run lots of other things we're gonna talk a lot today,
比如 shell 作为命令行界面，
about the shell which is the command line interface,
所以我们有了这些不同的程序在运行。
so we have all these different programs that are running.
而且这个运行应用程序的地方，
And this is the sort of world in which applications run
通常称为用户空间。
is usually called user space.
与此不同的是，这里有一个单独的程序，
And as distinct from that, there's a single program,
一个特殊的程序，它一直运行着，就是所谓的内核，
a special program, that's always running called the kernel
内核是计算机资源的守护者，
and the kernel is sort of the guardian of the resources of the computer,
它在你开机时第一个启动，
it's what first boots up you turn on the computer,
只有一个内核来管理数据
there's just one of it maintains data,
帮助管理进程，
to help manage each of these processes
并且内核也有很多的数据结构帮助访问，
and the kernel also means lots of data structures to help interface,
所有这些不同种类的硬件。
and all the different kinds of hardware,
这些用户程序需要使用的硬件。
these user programs need to use.
内核也有很多内置服务，
the kernel also has built in a bunch of services,
比如，
and so, for example
通常内核实现了一个文件系统，
there's typically a file system implementation inside the kernel,
它实现了文件名、文件内容和文件夹，
that implements things like file names and file contents and directories
并且知道如何将文件存储在磁盘上，
and understands how to store the files in the disk,
所以程序访问内核中的文件，
so your programs are going to talk to the files inside the kernel
然后文件系统访问磁盘。
and file implementations is going to talk to the disk.
在这门课上，
In this course,
我们主要关注内核内部发生的所有事情，
where we mostly focus on is all the things that has to happen inside the kernel,
还有用户程序和内核之间的接口，
and on the interfaces between user programs and the kernel,
还有内核里面的软件结构，
As well as the structure of the software inside the kernel.
所以我们很关心内核中的这些服务。
So we care a lot about these services inside the kernel.
其中之一是我提到过的文件系统，
One of them is a file system I mentioned,
还有对进程的管理，
there's also management of processes,
每个运行的程序被称为进程，
each of these running programs is called the process,
它有自己的内存，
and it has things like its own memory,
还有共享 CPU 时间。
for example as well as a share of the CPU time.
内核将进程作为内核服务进行管理，
So, kernel manages processes. as a kernel service,
内核管理内存的分配，
kernel manages the allocation of the memory,
不同的进程需要不同数量的内存，
the different processes need different amounts of memory,
内核复用、划分内存，
the kernel multiplexes and divides up the memory,
给不同的进程分配内存。
allocates the memory among all the different processes.
正如我提到的，内核影响文件系统，
The kernel as I mentioned influence the file system,
文件系统实际上分为三个逻辑部分或几个逻辑部分，
file system really comes into a three logical or a bunch of logical parts,
但现在，我们可以从
but for now, we can think of it
管理文件内容的角度来考虑它，
in terms of managing file content that's inside files,
找到内容在磁盘中的位置。
figuring out where on disk.
每个文件内容都是可以变化的，
Each file's content ought to live,
文件系统也在某种程度上管理一个命名空间，
file system also somewhat separately manages a name space,
每个文件都有一个名字，
that each file has a name
有一个层级目录，
and there's a hierarchy of directories,
每个目录中有多个文件，
every directory has a bunch of files in it,
所有这些都是由文件系统管理的。
all that's managed by the file system.
通常会有某种安全策略，
There's typically some sort of security arrangement,
有时也称为访问控制。
maybe we'll call it access control.
由内核决定，
Which the kernel decides
当一个进程想要读取，使用资源时，
that when a given process wants to read, use some resource,
或许是从磁盘读取东西，使用内存，
maybe read something from disk, use some memory,
内核内部的访问控制机制，
the access control machinery inside the kernel
可以决定它是允许还是不允许，
is what gets to decide yes it's allowed is that not allowed,
这也会很复杂，
that can get pretty complicated
如果我们讨论的是类似 Athena 的分时系统，
if we're talking about time sharing systems like Athena systems,
在那里，每个进程可能由不同的用户运行，
where there's you know each of these processes may be run by a different user
有不同的访问控制规则，
and have different access control rules,
是否允许访问其内容。
apply to what it's allowed to get at.
在一个成熟的操作系统中，
And in a real full-blown operating system
还有很多其他的服务，
turns out to be many, many other services,
你知道，通常有某种方式
you know there's typically some way
让不同的进程互相通信，
for different processes to talk to each other,
这称为进程间通信，
called inter process communication,
通常有很多软件使用网络，
there's typically a whole bunch of software associated with the network things,
比如用于网络通信的的 TCP/IP 协议，
like the TCP/IP protocols for talking the network,
通常也会支持声卡，
there's typically support for sound cards,
可能会有上百个不同磁盘驱动
there may be drivers for hundreds of different disks
and hundreds of different network cards,
所以在一个成熟的操作系统中，
so in a full-blown operating system
有大量的东西，
is a huge amount of stuff here
这可能会在内核中运行数百万行代码。
and this may run to millions of lines of code inside the kernel.
这是对内核内部的概述，
So that's sort of a quick overview of whats inside the kernel,
我们还对应用程序与内核交互，
we're also interested in how applications interact with the kernel
以及相关的接口定义感兴趣。
and what that interface looks like.
一般，所以这是内核的 API 。
The usual, so this is the API for the kernel.
应用程序如何访问内核，
How applications get at the kernel,
通常是通过系统调用来完成的，
typically that's done with something called system calls
它们看起来像是程序使用的函数调用，
and these are things that look like function calls that programs can make,
但实际上是跳入内核，
but actually jump into the kernel
并在执行内核中实现的系统调用，
and execute system call implementation in the kernel,
在这个讲座的后半部分，我会谈到这些，
I'll talk a bunch about that in the latter part of this lecture,
现在，只是让你初步了解一下。
for now just to give you a flavor here,
应用程序代码中
what a couple of different system calls
几个不同的系统调用是什么样的。
might look like in the source code of an application.
其中一个是，
One might be that
如果应用程序想要打开文件，
if you want an application wants to open a file,
它可以调用 open 系统调用。
and it calls the open system call,
把文件名传给 open 系统调用，
and tells the open system called the name of the file,
它想要打开一个名为 out 的文件并写入，
so maybe it wants to open a file for writing called out
下一个参数是 1 ，
and next argument here saying 1 in this case.
我想写那个文件，
Saying I want to write that file,
这个看起来像函数调用。
and so this thing that looks like a function call.
open 系统调用实际上是跳入内核的指定代码，
It opens the system calls actually special code that jumps into the kernel
内核可以获得这些参数，
and the kernel can retrieve these arguments,
执行一些实现 open 的内核代码，
executes some kernel code that implements open,
可能是访问磁盘，然后返回一个值，
maybe talks to the disk, and then returns a value
这就是文件描述符， fd 表示文件描述符。
and that's this file descriptor, as fd stands for file descriptor,
程序可以使用文件描述符来访问这个打开的文件。
which is the program can then use as a handle to refer to this open file.
如果你想写入一个文件，
If you want to write to a file,
需要使用系统调用 write ，
the system call did, to do that is called write,
你必须向它传递一个文件描述符，
you have to pass it one of these file descriptors,
跟 open 返回的类似，
the same was returned by open,
这些是系统调用中传递的参数。
these are arguments that are passed in the system call.
从程序到内核，
From the program into the kernel,
你给它一个指向一个字符缓冲区的指针，
and you give it a pointer to a buffer of characters,
在 C 语言中，一个简单的方法是，
so an easy way to do that in the C programming language,
使用双引号，然后加上字符串，
which these examples are written by as double quotes then the string,
字符串中的 \n 表示换行，
the bytes of the string backslash n is a new line
第三个参数是字符数。
and the third argument is the count of characters.
如果想写入，这里是关键，
If you want to write so this really gets point,
把内存中的这个地址传过去，
pass this address in memory,
告诉内核，请把这个地址的 6 个字节
so you're telling the kernel look, please write 6 bytes from this address
写入到这个文件描述符关联的文件中。
to the file that this file descriptor refers to.
一个更有意思的系统调用
A much more exciting system call the encounter
是 fork 系统调用，
is the fork system call fork is the system call,
它创建一个新的进程，
that creates a new process,
并返回一个与调用方相同的进程，
and returns actually creates a process that's identical to the caller
fork 返回新创建进程的进程标识符 pid 。
and fork returns the identifier the process identifier pid of the new process.
更复杂的[]，我们还会听到更多关于这方面的内容。
More complicated than [], we'll hear more about this.
同样，这些看起来像函数调用，
So again, these are all look like function calls,
但是系统调用很特殊，因为它们跳入内核。
but the system calls are special because they jump into the kernel.
这是初步了解，稍后我们会看到更多。
That's taste, we'll see more later.
这是一个简单的概述，
That is a sort of quick overview,
我想提一下为什么我发现操作系统的学习，
I wanna just mention why I find a operating the study of operating systems,
既有挑战性，又十分有趣。
to be both a challenging and interesting.
为什么值得
Why you know why it's maybe worth,
intellectually worth taking a course in this area.
这很难的一个原因是，环境是难以应对的，
So, one reason why it's hard is that the environment is unforgiving,
内核的编程环境是难以应对的，
programming environment inside the kernels unforgiving,
因为当你在编程时，
because you're, your when you're programming,
当你修改或扩展内核，
when you're modifying the kernel or extending the kernel
或编写新的操作系统内核时，
or writing a new operating system kernel,
你提供的是其他人认为已经存在的基础设施，
you're providing the infrastructure that everybody else assumes
用来运行他们的程序。
is already present to run their programs.
任何人编写应用程序都在操作系统上运行，
And then everybody else gets an operating system under their program
当他们编写普通应用程序时，
when they write ordinary application programs,
但是当我们构建操作系统时，
but when we build operating systems
操作系统下直接是硬件，
what we get is the hardware underneath our operating system
结果是更难处理。
which turns out to be more difficult to deal with.
在本课程中，
In this course,
我们用到一个叫 QEMU 的硬件模拟器，
we we get to use a hardware simulator called QEMU.
它模拟一个 CPU 和一台计算机，
That simulates a CPU and a computer
这样做会好一点，
and that makes a little bit better,
但它仍然是困难的编程环境。
but it's still a kind of a difficult, environment programming.
另一个困难又有趣的原因是，
Another reason why it's hard and interesting is
当你在设计操作系统时，
because if you're designing and operating system,
必须解决一系列矛盾。
you have to satisfy a bunch of tensions,
这需要真正的设计思想，
that require real design thought.
其中之一是，你希望操作系统要有效率。
So one is that you'd like your operating system to be both efficient.
这通常意味着它在接近硬件的底层上运行，
Which often means that it operates at a low level close to the hardware,
但是为了便于使用，
but for ease of use,
而且现实生活中的人必须
and because real live people have to write programs
使用你的操作系统编写程序，
that use your operating system,
所以我们希望它也是一个正确的高层次抽象。
we'd like it also to be a right abstract high-level.
一个可移植的接口，
A portable interfaces
提供简单的抽象接口需要巧妙的技巧，
and it's a neat trick to provide a abstract interfaces that are simple.
便携的但也是高效的。
A portable but they are also efficient.
另一个矛盾是，
Another tension is
我们要提供一个非常强大的操作系统服务，
that we'd like to provide a very powerful operating system services,
让操作系统可以承担很多责任。
so that the operating system can shoulder a lot of the burden.
运行程序像强大的操作系统服务。
Running programs like a powerful operating system services.
但是，我们也希望有简单的接口。
But, we also want to have simple interfaces,
我们不想让程序员使用
that we don't want a tremendously complex
一个非常复杂、难以理解的接口，
hard to understand interfaces for programmers to use,
因为我也不会去理解它们，
because I'm not going to understand them,
他们会发现它很难使用，
and they may find it hard to use,
所以这是一个很简单的 API ，
so this is really simple API,
所以可以提供一个简单的接口，
and so this is possible to do to provide a simple interfaces,
并在内部拥有强大机制，
that have powerful a machinery inside them,
这一直在寻找。
will always be searching for.
简单的接口提供强大的服务，
Sort of simple interfaces provide a powerful services.
嘿， Robert ，有人提问。
Hey, Robbery, we've got a question in the chat.
系统调用跳入内核有什么特别之处，
What is unique slash different about saying system calls jump into the kernel,
与跳转到另一个函数的标准函数调用相比。
i.e as opposed to a standard function call that jumps to another function.
好的，内核是一段始终驻留的代码，
Well, the kernel has, the kernel is, a piece of code that's always resident,
它具有特权，
that has special privileges
因为内核在机器启动时加载，
that were that because it booted the machine booted the kernel,
内核具有特权，
kernel has special privileges,
它可以直接访问各种硬件，
it can get directly at all kinds of hardware,
比如磁盘，普通用户程序不能访问，
like the disk device that ordinary user programs can't get at,
所以如果你执行一个普通函数调用，
so if you make a an ordinary function call,
你调用的函数没有，
the function your calling doesn't get it,
没有任何关于硬件的特权，
doesn't get any special privileges with respect to the hardware,
而你在内核执行系统调用，
whereas if you make a system call into the kernel,
后面我们会详细讨论这是如何工作的，
we'll talk about how this works,
这就像当系统调用跳到，
but that ends up as when it jumps into,
跳到内核时，
when the system call jumps into the kernel,
然后内核中的系统调用实现获得所有这些特权，
system call implementation in the kernel then gets all these special privileges,
这样它就可以修改各种敏感的受保护的硬件资源，
so that it can modify all kinds of sensitive and protected hardware resources,
比如直接访问硬盘，
like for example getting directly at the hard disk.
我们稍后会看到更多关于这些的细节。
We'll see a lot more detail for all this shortly.
好的，我们要说的最后一个矛盾是，
Okay, so a final tension that we want
所有操作系统都需要满足你的需求，
that all operating systems need to satisfy your gonna give programs,
尽可能的灵活，
as much flexibility as you can,
你不想限制它们，
you don't want to constrain them,
所以你想要很灵活的接口。
so you want to have very flexible interfaces.
但是确实需要在一定程度上约束程序，
But you do need to constrain program somewhat,
因为你必须有一些安全概念。
because you absolutely have to have some notion of security.
我们喜欢编程，编程很自由，
We love for programs programs complete freedom,
但它不能是完全自由的，
but it can't be complete can't be really complete,
因为我们不想让程序直接访问硬件，
because we don't want programs to get directly at the hardware
或者干扰其他程序，
or to interfere with other programs
或者在某种程度上干扰
or a sort of be able to interfere
操作系统本身的操作。
with the operation of the operating system itself.
这就是你们需要知道的。
So, these are all you know.
做好这项工作是可能的，
It's possible to do a good job
我们将对此进行大量讨论，
and we'll talk a lot about it,
但这总是令人费解，
but it's always a bit of a puzzle
在这两列中同时提供这两个属性。
to provide sort of both of these properties in both of these columns.
另一个让操作系统设计变得困难和有趣的是，
Another thing that makes OS design hard and interesting is
操作系统提供了很多功能和服务，
that operating systems provide a lot of features and a lot of services,
但它们实际上倾向于交互，
but they actually tend to interact
而且有时以奇怪的方式进行交互，
and sometimes in odd ways
这需要很多思考，
that require a lot of thought,
即使是我给出的简单示例。
so even the simple examples I gave.
使用 open 和 fork ，这两个交互，
With open and fork, those two interact actually
如果一个程序使用 open 系统调用分配文件描述符，
if a program allocates a file descriptor with the open system call,
然后使用 fork 分配相同的程序。
and then that same program fork.
fork 的语义是，
And the semantics of fork just turned out to be
你创建一个新进程，它是当前进程的副本，
that you create a new process that's a copy of the current process,
你打开的这个文件描述符，
this file descriptor you opened,
实际上是一个副本，
if that's truly to be a copy,
这个文件描述符仍然在子进程中存在并可用,
this file descriptor still has to be present and usable in the child,
所以必须仔细考虑，
and so that has to be thought,
这就是文件，
through that is the files,
打开的文件描述符以这种方式与 fork 交互，
the opened file descriptors interact with fork in this interesting way
必须找到让子进程能读取到
and somebody has to figure out should the child be able to get at,
fork 调用之前创建的文件描述符，
the file descriptors created before fork is called
答案是肯定的，
and the answer has to be yes,
这就是我们要看的操作系统。
the operating systems we're going to look at.
好的，其他有趣的事情
Alright and so other things that
我已经提过了，
are turned out to be interesting I already mentioned,
操作系统必须满足各种各样的用途，
that operating systems have to cater to a wide variety of uses,
同样的操作系统适用于数据库服务器和智能手机，
the same OS used both for database servers and smartphones, for example.
而且操作系统，随着时间的推移，
And operating systems, as time goes on,
你运行的硬件，得到的硬件，
the hardware that you run, hardware you get,
典型的计算机会发生变化，
but typical computers changes,
可能使用超高速的固态硬盘存储替代机械硬盘。
maybe get superfast ssd storage instead of mechanical hard drive, for example.
大概十五年前，
And about fifteen years ago,
多核计算机从稀有发展到无处不在，
multi core computers went from being rare curiosities to being pervasive
最近我们看到了数量级的提速，
and and recently we've seen order of magnitude speedups
和网络操作速度，
and how fast networks operate
所以这些都需要重新思考。
and so all these require rethinks.
定期介绍操作系统是如何设计的。
Periodically of how operating systems are designed.
这些就是
Now so so those are those are,
你可能选择这门课的原因。
sort of intellectually why you might take the course,
还有一些更实际的原因，
there's also some more practical reasons,
你选择这门课的原因，
why you might be glad to have taken this course,
一个是如果你对计算机内部发生的事情感兴趣，
one is if you're interested in what happens inside computers,
想知道并探寻计算机内部的秘密，
what goes on and saw under the hood a sort of in secret,
当你打开计算机时，
when you turn on your computer,
这是一个很好的课程，
this is a good course to take,
类似地，如果你喜欢基础设施，
similarly if you like infrastructure
也就是如果你喜欢建立一种服务，
that is if if you enjoy building a sort of services
其他程序可以使用的服务。
that other programs can then use them.
当然，这基本上都是关于基础设施的，
This is of course essentially all about infrastructure,
因为这就是操作系统。
because that's that's what operating systems are.
如果你曾经花费大量时间来跟踪应用程序代码中的 bug ，
If you ever need to spend a lot of time tracking down bugs in application code
或跟踪安全问题，
or tracking down security problems
通常会设计到了解操作系统内部发生了什么，
often that involves understanding what was going on inside the operating system,
因为最终是操作系统实施了很多安全措施，
because it's ultimately the operating system that enforces a lot of security,
当事情发生错误时，
and when things go wrong,
操作系统必须收拾残局，
it's the operating system has to pick up the pieces,
通常设计到跟踪 bug ，然后最终。
so that's often involved in tracking down bugs and finally.
在聊天中有两个问题，
Two more questions from the chat,
第一个是，
so the first is
对于应用程序开发人员来说，
how important is it for application developers,
真正深入理解操作系统有多重要，
to truly deeply understand the operating systems
对于开发应用来说，
of developing their applications for,
它们是否需要称为专家。
do they necessarily need to be experts.
你不需要成为专家，
You don't have to be an expert,
但是如果你花费大量时间
but if you spend a lot of time
开发、维护和调试应用程序，
developing and maintaining and debugging applications,
你最终会对操作系统有很多了解，
you'll eventually end up knowing a lot about the operating system,
无论你是有意或无意，
whether you, whether you meant to or not,
它就出现了，而且你经常被迫理解它。
just it just comes up and you're often forced to understand.
第二个问题是，
And the second question is,
像 Python 这样的高级编程语言是否直接使用系统调用，
do high-level programming languages like python use system calls directly,
是否为了方便编写了内置的包装器。
are there built in slash wrappers for convenience.
很多高级语言在某种程度上是从操作系统中转移出来的，
A lot of high-level languages are sort of at one of move from system calls,
这是正确的。
that's absolutely true.
所以，部分原因是许多语言
So, but partially because a lot of languages
想要提供可移植的环境，
want to provide portable a portable environment,
可以运行在许多不同的操作系统上，
that works on many different operating systems,
因此它们不一定要致力于
so they can't necessarily commit to
任何一种操作系统的特定系统调用，
the specific system calls or any one operating system.
所以答案是，
So, the answer,
我想问题的答案是，
the question I think is
如果你使用 Python ，
if you use python,
你多少与系统调用接口有些隔离。
you're somewhat insulated from the system call interface,
Python 内部当然会做，
you know internally of course python makes,
调用系统调用来完成它的工作。
has to make system calls get its work done.
当然，在 Python 和许多其他语言中，
And, certainly in python and many other languages,
通常有一种方法可以直接进入系统调用，
there is usually a way to get directly at the system calls
无论你使用什么操作系统。
whatever your operating system, you're running on.
想提问的各位同学，
And folks for questions,
你可以自己提问，
you can just feel free to jump in yourself and ask questions,
不一定需要通过聊天提出问题。
you don't need to go through the chat.
好的。
Okay.
好的，抱歉，现在我要花几分钟，
Alright, sorry, I'm going to spend a couple of minutes now
讨论 6.S081 的课程结构，
talking about a class structure of 6.S081,
然后再回到技术内容部分，
before switching back to actual technical content.
这里有一个课程的网站，
So there is a website for the course,
我现在不想写出来，
which I don't want to write out just now,
但是你可以在谷歌上搜索 6.S081 找到它。
but it's you can find it by looking for 6.S081 on Google.
这个网站有一个课程表，
And the website, has a schedule,
课程表上有作业，还有实验作业。
it has the assignments on the schedule that has the lab assignments.
它也有关于课程结构的其他信息，
And it has the sort of information about course structure,
比如课程的评分标准。
like the grading policy on it.
你需要跟踪的另一个重要资源是 Piazza 。
The other big resource you're gonna wanna keep track of piazza.
我想，来这里的每个人都是通过 Piazza 。
I guess, everybody was here got here by way piazza,
但是还有，
but as well as,
所以我们定期来做两件主要的事情，
so we used periodically for two main things,
一是人们能够对实验作业提出问题，
one is as a way of people being able to ask questions about the lab assignments,
工作人员会试着回答这些问题，
and a course staff will try to answer these questions,
你们也可以完全自由地回答彼此的问题，
but you should feel absolutely free to answer each other's questions as well
在 Piazza 上发生的另一件事是，
and the other big thing that happens on piazza,
如果有课程公告，就会发布在上面，
if there's announcements there's any announcements about the course.
我们会把公告放在 Piazza 上，
We'll put the announcement on piazza,
所以你应该关注 Piazza 上的公告，
so you should keep an eye on piazza for announcements,
即使你不用它来寻找实验帮助。
even if you're not using it for lab help.
是的。
Yeah.
课程的很大一部分就是这些课程。
The one of the big parts of course is that these lectures.
这个讲座会涉及到操作系统的基本理念。
Lectures will cover basic ideas of operating systems.
有些课程会详细研究 xv6 的代码，
Some of the lectures will be devoted to detailed a study of the code in xv6,
这是我们的小型教学操作系统，
which is our small teaching operating system
讨论它是如何工作的，
and so talk about how it works,
我们会在课程中查看代码，演示代码执行过程，
we'll look at the code and show the code executing during lectures,
另外，在很多课程之前
and in addition, before many of the lectures,
我们会先阅读书中的作业，
we'll be assignments reading assignments from a book,
这本书描述了 xv6 是如何运行的，
that sort of describes how xv6 operates
以及为什么它是这样设计的。
and why it's designed that way.
所以你应该在上课前阅读，
So you do the readings before the class,
这样就能听懂课程上的讨论，
so they do understand the discussion in the class,
一些课程专门讲授背景知识，
some of the lectures are devoted to background
帮助你做实验。
to help you do the labs.
比如 C 语言是如何工作的，
So, like about C works of,
RISC-V ，也就是我们要使用的微处理器，
how the RISC-V which is the microprocessor that we'll be using,
你们会发现这对理解如何做实验很有帮助，
that you'll find helpful in understanding how to do the labs
在课程快结束的时候，
and towards the end of the course,
我们会用一些课讨论一些操作系统论文，
we'll spend some lectures discussing some operating system papers,
研究论文和该领域的一些经典论文，
research papers and some classic papers in the field,
会要求你们在课程前阅读这些论文，
which you will ask that you read before the lecture
然后我们会在课程中讨论这些论文。
and then we'll sort of talk about the papers during the lecture,
对于所有的讲座，
for all the lectures are almost all the lectures,
我们要求你在讲座之前，
we ask that you submit a question about the reading,
提交一个关于所读文章的问题。
for the lecture before the actual time of the lecture.
你们中的很多人都参加了这次讲座，谢谢你们。
Which many or all of you did for this lecture for which thank you,
我们会查看这些问题来帮助我们。
and we will read those questions to help us.
指导我们讨论什么，
Guide us about what to talk about
我们会努力回答尽可能多的问题，
and we'll try to answer as many of the questions as we can,
尽管很少有时间，不过我们没有时间回答所有问题。
although there's rarely time, unfortunately for us to answer all of them.
课程的下一个重要部分是实验。
The next big part of the course of the labs.
几乎每周都有一个编程实验，
There's a programming lab do, almost every week
实验的目的是，
and the point of the labs is
帮助你亲身体验
to help you get hands on experience
实现和使用操作系统。
with implementing and using operating systems.
下周到期的一个实验是，
A lab that's due next week is
关于如何编写
actually about using about writing applications
调用系统调用的应用程序，
that make the call the system calls,
随后我们会讨论。
we'll be talking about.
与此之后的大多数实验不同，
Whereas most of those labs after that are involved,
要么实现基本的操作系统功能，
you either implementing basic operating system features
或想 xv6 操作系统添加内核扩展，
or adding a kernel extensions to the xv6 operating system,
最后一个实验，
the very last lab and one
是添加一个网络栈，和网络驱动程序，
in which you actually add a network stack and a network driver,
以便能够通过网络
so you'll be able to connect in over the network
to the operating system that you run.
如果你对实验有问题，
You should, if you have problems with the lab's,
助教会在办公时间提供帮助。
they'll be office hours that TAs will hold.
你也可以把问题发布到 Piazza 上，
In addition you can post questions to piazza
而且通常可以从 Piazza 上获得有用的答案，
and very often you'll be able to get useful answers from piazza
比在办公时间更快。
more quickly than from office hours.
我们欢迎你讨论实验，
We welcome you discussing the labs talking about the labs,
讨论如何设计实验解决方案，
talking about how to design the lab solutions,
但是我们要求不要看别人的解决方案。
but we ask you please do not look at other people's solutions.
重复一遍，你编写的所有代码都应该是自己的，
Relapse, please all the code you write should be your own
而且你不应该分享代码或查看其他解决方案。
and you shouldn't share code or a look at other solutions.
评分，当然，今年主要由实验决定的。
Grading, of course, will be mostly determined from the labs this year,
所以 70% 的成绩将是根据你的实验结果，
so 70% of the grade will be, based on whether or not your lab,
你提交的代码是否通过测试，
you submit passes the tests
我们评分使用我们提供的相同的测试，
and we for grading, we run the same tests that we supply you,
所以如果你的实验通过了我们提供的所有实验，
so if your lab passes all the tests that we give you,
你就可以得到实验的全部分数。
the chance to show you that full credit for the lab.
20% 的分数来自实验检查会议，
20% of the grade is going to be from lab checkoff meetings
你们每个人都将随机选择几个实验，
for each of you will pick a couple of randomly selected labs
有一个小组将与你们交谈，
and one of the teams will talk to you
询问你们关于实现实验的问题，
and ask you questions about your implementation
确保你们真的理解发生了什么。
just to make sure that are you really understand what's going on.
这是实验检查。
It's a lab check offs.
还剩 10% 。
There's a 10% remaining.
很多，比如是或否，一或零的事，
A lot of, kind of be, like a yes or no, one or zero type of thing
或者他们会，
or would they be,
比如答对了部分问题，
like could someone get, like if they answered some of the questions right,
但不是所有问题都答对了，
but not all the questions right,
当他们是这种情况时，分数是怎样的。
when they get in between, so the grade.
你知道，我还没有想过这件事。
You know I haven't thought this through,
当然有部分学分的情况，但是。
there's certainly room for partial credit, but.
它不是二选一的，
It's not, it won't be binary,
你当然可以获得部分学分。
it'll definitely be you can receive partial credit.
好的。
Okay.
最后的 10% 是由家庭作业
The last 10% is going to be driven by the homework
以及讲座和 Piazza 的参与决定的。
and participation during lecture and piazza.
今年不会有考试或小测验。
There will be no exams or quizzes this year.
所以，这意味着大部分的，
And so what, that means is that most of the,
你知道 90% 的成绩是由实验决定的。
you know 90% of the grade is being driven by the lab.
所以你应该花很多时间在实验上，
So you should spend a lot of time in the labs,
确保你早点开始，
make sure that you start early
有足够的时间完成实验，并解决 bug ，
and have enough time to complete them and work out bugs
以获得满分。
in order to get full credit.
你知道，因此这是一门
And you know as a result of that this is going to be a
非常实用的面向软件的课程。
very kind of hands-on software oriented course.
关于课程组织，还有什么问题吗？
Any questions about the machinery of the course?
在聊天中有几个问题。
We've got a couple questions in chat.
第一个是组织管理的问题，
So the first is a logistical question,
当前， 6.S081 没有像往常一样在系统主修课程中，
currently 6.S081 isn't listed as usual for the system's concentration in the [],
以后有没有增加课程的计划。
are there plans added to the list of classes later.
我想因为它不是批准的高级研究生课程，
I think for that because it's not an AAGS,
它是高级本科课程，
it's an AUS,
它不能满足安排要求，
it can't be used to fulfill arrange requirements,
所以它不是研究生水平的课程。
so it's not a graduate level class.
但是，我们有唯一的家庭作业来提交问题，
But, and then we have is the only homework to submit questions
看看日历似乎是这样。
looking at the calendar that appears to be the case.
除非我忘了什么，我想就是这样的。
Unless I'm forgetting something, I think that's the case, yes.
那么，有没有分数比例的情况，
So have, are there gonna be cutoffs for grades,
像是百分之 X 的人得 A ，百分之 Y 得 B 等等。
like X percent gets in A, Y percent gets a B etc.
不，不，你知道我们努力给学生自由。
No, no, you know we're going to try to free student estimate.
我的评价是你对材料理解得好坏，
I'm impression of how well you've understood the material,
并在此基础上给出一个分数，
and assign a grade based on that,
所以不会有预先设定的比例。
so there's no predetermined cut offs.
好的，还有其他问题吗？
Alright anything else?
好的，对于聊天中
Alright, just real quick for folks in the chat
询问主修要求的人来说，
asking about the concentration requirement,
我不是百分之百确定，
I'm not a hundred percent certain,
但 6.S081 不是，
but 6.S081 is not,
它是课程获得正式编号之前的一个临时编号，
it's a temporary number before the class gets official one,
所以它不会出现在任何地方，
so it certainly won't be listed anywhere,
如果你需要它来实现主修课程，
if you need it to fulfill a concentration,
我想你最好的选择是填写一份请愿书，
I think your best bet is probably to fill out a petition
或给 Katrina Kurtz 发送邮件，
or to email somebody like Katrina Kurtz,
查看是什么状态，
to see a what the status is,
我们无法控制
we don't control, you know,
哪些课程满足这些要求。
what what classes fill these kind of requirements, unfortunately.
这门课将使用什么语言，将使用 C 语言。
And for what language will be using the class, will be in C.
好的。
Alright, um.
好的，对于这堂课剩下的时间，
Alright, for the rest of the lecture,
我想谈一下，
I want to talk about how
系统调用看起来像应用程序。
what system calls look like applications.
你知道，因为系统调用
And you know since the system calls
是操作系统提供服务的接口，
are the interface to the services that the operating system provides
所以这些系统实际是什么样，
is actually pretty important what those systems look like,
应用程序从系统调用中得到什么，
what applications expect from system calls and how they behave,
所以理解接口是什么样子是值得的。
so it's worth understanding what the interface looks like.
你将在第一个实验中使用我们谈到的系统调用，
You'll be using the system calls we talk about in the first lab,
在后续的实验中，
and extending and improving the implementation,
扩展和增强这些系统调用的内部实现。
internal implementation of these system calls in subsequent labs.
我们将演示一些程序的简单示例。
What we're gonna do is show some simple examples of little programs.
它调用系统调用，我将在 xv6 中运行它们。
That call system calls and I'll run them in xv6 four you.
我将运行它们，
I'm gonna run them,
xv6 是一个简单的类 unix 操作系统，
the xv6 is a, it's a unix, a simplified unix like operating system,
unix 是一个古老的操作系统，
unix is a old operating system,
至少作为许多当前操作系统的基础，
that's at least intellectual basis for many present-day operating systems,
它使用非常广泛，
such as Linux and OS X it's in very common use,
xv6 我们的教学操作系统要简单地多，
xv6 our teaching operating system is much simpler
在某种程度上收到 unix 的启发，
and sort of inspired by unix
具有相同的整体结构，
and has the same overall structure,
但是比任何真正的 unix 操作系统都要简单。
but is dramatically simpler than any real unix operating system.
它足够简单，
It's simple enough that hopefully,
你可以直接阅读
you know it would be relatively straightforward,
所有的源码，
for you to read all the source code,
同时阅读这本书，
as well as read the book,
在几周时间内。
in a couple of weeks.
当然在本学期，
Certainly during the semester
为了理解所有 xv6 内部发生的事情。
in order to kind of understand all of what happens inside xv6.
xv6 运行在 RISC-V 处理器上，
xv6 runs on the RISC-V processor, RISC-V microprocessor,
这也是最近 6.004 课程使用的微处理器。
and this is the same microprocessor that's the focus of recent 6.004.
所以，你们中的很多人可能对 RISC-V 指令集有相当多的了解。
So many of you may actually know quite a bit about the RISC-V instruction set.
理论上你可以在 RISC-V 计算机上运行 xv6 ，
In theory you could run xv6 on top of a RISC-V computer
也已经有人这么做了。
and people done that.
但是我们要在 QEMU 机器仿真器下运行，
But we're going to run it under the QEMU machine emulator,
只需要把我们得到的写下来。
just write this down we got.
我们的操作系统是 xv6 ，
Our operating system is xv6,
运行在 RISC-V 微处理器之上，
runs on RISC-V microprocessor
不仅是 RISC-V 微处理器，
and not just RISC-V microprocessor,
还有周围的一些硬件，
but we assume a certain amount of surrounding hardware,
比如内存和磁盘。
like a memory and a disk,
还有控制台界面，我们可以访问它。
and console interface for us to talk to it.
我们实际上是在 QEMU 机器模拟器下运行的。
We actually run under the QEMU machine simulator.
也是在 Linux 下运行的。
So that which runs under Linux.
所以你可以在没有硬件的情况下运行 xv6 。
So all you can actually run xv6 without having that hardware.
好的，现在切换到演示代码。
Okay, so kind of switch to show the code.
好的，那么第一件事是，
Alright, so, first thing is,
我已经在我的笔记本电脑上安装了 xv6 ，
I've setup xv6 on my laptop,
我要运行它，输入 make qemu ，
I'm going to run it type make qemu,
你会在实验中发现做了更多的工作，
but you'll find yourself doing quite a bit during the labs,
它编译 xv6 ，是用 C 编写的，
which compiles xv6 it's written in C,
所以它使用 C 编译器编译，
so it's compiled with C compiler,
我应该先输入 make clean 清理一下，
maybe I'll make clean for you,
这样你们就可以看到实际的编译过程，
so you can see the actual compilation
我再输入 make qemu ，
and I might make qemu,
它开始编译和构建 xv6 内核，
which has the effect of compiling and building xv6 kernel
以及所有用户程序，
and all the user processes
然后在 QEMU 模拟器上运行。
and then running them under the QEMU emulator.
编译过程会花费一些时间。
Takes a moment around the compiles.
好的。
Yeah.
现在我们启动并运行 xv6 ，
And now we're up and running xv6,
你看到的 shell 中的 $ 符号，
and the dollar sign prompt you see as the shell,
shell 是 xv6 的命令行界面，
which is the command line interface to xv6,
仿造 unix 上的 shell 。
modeled after the shell on unix,
也是如果你登录到 Athena 系统，
which is if you log into Athena organization
就像 Athena shell 显示的那样。
and it's it's like the shell that Athena shows you.
xv6 本身很小，它附带了一些使用程序，
Xv6 itself tiny and it comes with a small number of utility programs,
包含比如 ls 程序，
and including for example the ls program
运行 ls ，它会给出一个所有文件的列表，
which about to run run ls and it gives me a list of all the files
xv6 只有二十多个文件，
and xv6 of which there are only about two dozen
包括 grep kill mkdir 和 rm ，
including things like grep and kill and mkdir rm,
这些是我们熟悉的 unix 实用程序。
which may be familiar to us as unix utilities.
好的，我要演示的第一个程序是，
Okay, the first program, I'm gonna show you
演示系统调用 copy ，
to illustrate system calls is a program called copy.
这里的代码只有一页。
Here's the source is just a page.
你在这里看到的程序，从第 8 行开始，
So what you're seeing here is a program that starts on line eight
main 是 C 语言程序的一种约定，
and main is that sort of convention for C programs,
在第 12 行有一个循环，
it sits in a loop at line twelve,
一遍又一遍地
and over and over again,
在第 13 行读取一些数据作为输入，
it reads some data as input and on line thirteen,
然后在第 16 行将刚才读取的数据写入输出。
and then writes the data just read his output on line sixteen.
运行 copy ，在 xv6 中，等待读取输入，
By run copy, in xv6, it's waitng to read input,
如果我输入一些内容，
if I type some input,
它读取并返回给我。
reads it and spits it back up to me.
很简单的程序，只是做输入输出。
Very simple program just does io.
就像我提到的，如果你不是很了解 C 语言，
It's really see as I mentioned, if you don't already know C,
Kernighan 和 Ritchie 编写的
it's worthwhile getting
C 程序设计语言很值得阅读。
the standard C programming language book by Kernighan and Ritchie.
我想在课程网站上有更完整的参考资料，
And I think there's a more full reference to it on the course website
想你解释使用 C 编程的直接方法。
which explains to you and very straightforward way how to program in C.
是的，像我之前提到的，
Yeah, as I mentioned before,
我们编写这个程序，
we even write this program
使用了两个实际上是三个系统调用，
makes two really three system calls
read write exit 系统调用。
read, write and exit, our system calls.
如果你看第 13 行的 read 调用，
If you look at the call to read on line thirteen,
它有三个参数，
it takes three arguments,
第一个参数是一个文件描述符，
the first argument is a file descriptor
它实际上是对之前打开的文件的引用。
which is really a reference to a previously opened file.
shell 确保当程序启动时，
And the shell, ensures that when a program starts,
默认它的文件描述符 0 连接到控制台输入，
by default it's file descriptor zero is connected to the console input
它的文件描述符 1 连接到控制台输出，
and its file descriptor one is connected to the console output
这就是为什么我能对 copy 程序输入，并查看输出。
and that's why I was able to type to this copy program and see the output.
你知道，这些文件描述符期望，
You know these file descriptors are expected
程序期望这些文件描述符已经打开，
the program expected these file descriptors have been previously opened
并由 shell 为其设置。
and set up by the shell for it.
0 1 文件描述符是 unix 的普遍约定，
And zero one file descriptors, pervasive unix convention,
很多 unix 程序希望
many, many unix programs expect to
[误：从文件描述符 1 读取]，
[read from file descriptor one]
读取文件描述符 0 ，并写入文件描述符 1 。
and read file descriptor zero and write to file descriptor one.
read 的第二个参数是一个指向内存的指针。
A second argument to read is a pointer to some memory.
程序告诉操作系统
Where the program is asking the operating system
从这个内存地址读取数据，
to read data into that address in memory,
这是 buf 参数，
so that's the buf argument
在第 10 行，在栈上分配了 64 字节的内存。
and line ten allocate 64 bytes of memory on the stack,
供 read 读取。
for read to read into.
read 的第三个参数是
And the third argument to read is
程序想要读入的最大字节数，
the maximum number of bytes that the program wants to read
而 buf 的大小最大是 64 字节，
and the size of buf as just sixty maximum 64 bytes,
所以 read 读取最多 64 字节，
so the read call reads up to 64 bytes
从文件描述符 0 连接的地方，
from whatever is connected to file descriptor zero
在本例中， 0 就是连接到我的终端。
and that was my terminal in this example,
read 的返回值可能是读取到的字节数，
the return value from read it either it may be sure of the number of bytes read,
这里是 6 ，
which would be six and a piece of,
我输入 xyzzy 。
typing xyzzy by.
read 也可以从文件中读取，
Read might be reading from a file,
如果到达文件末尾，
if it gets to the end of the file,
没有更多字节，
there's no more bytes,
read 将返回 0 。
read will return zero.
如果发生其他错误，
And then some other error occurred,
比如文件描述符不存在，
like the file descriptor doesn't exist,
read 可能会返回 -1 。
read may return minus one.
在很多例子中，比如在第 16 行。
And so in many of these examples like on line sixteen there.
我的示例代码没有检查系统调用返回是否有错误，
I don't, my example code doesn't check system call returns for errors.
但是你应该比我更小心，
But you should be more careful than me,
你应该弄清楚系统调用是如何返回错误的，
the you should figure out how system calls reflect errors,
通常是返回 -1 ，
it's usually a minus one return value
并检查所有系统调用的返回是否有错误。
and check all system called returns for errors.
如果你想知道系统调用参数和返回值是什么，
And if you want to know what the system call arguments and return values are,
这里有一个表格，我想是在书中的第 2 章。
there's a table and I think chapter two in the book,
解释了所有 xv6 系统调用参数和返回值。
explains all of the xv6 system call arguments and return values.
关于 read 系统调用的问题。
The question regarding the read syscall.
如果我们将最大读取字节数
What if we set the max read bytes to
设置为 buf 大小加 1 ，
size of buf to one plus size of buf big,
所以如果我们尝试读取的大小超过该大小会怎样。
so what if we try to read more than the size.
是的，如果有 65 个字节要读取，
Yeah, then if there was 65 bytes to read,
操作系统会很高兴地
then the operating system would happily
把这 65 个字节复制到你提供的内存上，
will just copy those sixty-five bytes to the memory that you provide,
当然还有栈上的其他东西，
and of course there's something else on the stack up there,
可能是返回程序计数器，
maybe the return program counter
或者参数或其他东西，
or an argument or something
所以如果你传入 65 个字节，
and so if you pass 65,
那么你就是让内核
then you're inviting a kernel
在栈上意想不到的位置写入垃圾数据。
to write junk to an unexpected place in your stack.
因此，这是一个 bug ，
And so that's a bug
它可能会导致你的程序崩溃。
and it may cause your [] to crash,
或者做一些其他意想不到的事情，
or do something else unexpected,
因此作为一个程序员，在这里必须小心，
so as a programmer, you have to be careful here,
没有人使用 C 语言这样使用接口，
there's nobody writing in C with these kind of interfaces,
很容易编写的代码，
it's very very easy to write code
编译器可以通过，并且可以运行，
that the compiler is happy with and will run
但是做的是错误的事。
but absolutely does the wrong thing.
那太糟糕了，但事情就是这样。
So that's too bad but it's the way it is.
好的，有一件事需要注意，
Okay, one thing to note is
这里的 copy 程序和 read write 系统调用，
that this copy program and indeed the read write system calls,
它们不关心数据的格式，
they don't care about the format of data,
它们读写，
they're reading or writing
只是在 copy 程序中读写，再读写。
they just read and write read and write in this copy program.
只是处理八位字节，使用八位字节流。
Just deal with eight bit bytes with screams of eight bit bytes.
如何解释它们，完全取决于应用程序。
How you interpret them is totally up to the application,
应用程序可能会解析数据记录作为 C 代码，
so the application maybe parse these data records or as C source code,
或者其他的格式。
or who knows what.
操作系统只知道这是八位字节流。
The operating system, the only things in terms of a stream of eight bit bytes.
好的，所以 copy 可以假设
Okay, so copy, assumed this code, my copy I can assume
文件描述符已经设置好，
that the file descriptors are already set up,
但是我们需要有一种方法来创建文件描述符。
but we need to need to have a way to create file descriptors.
创建文件描述符的最直接的方法是使用 open 系统调用，
And the most straightforward way to do that is with the open system call,
这是一个调用 open 的程序代码，
and so here's the source for a program that called open,
那个，
That,
我使用 open 系统调用。
I use the open system call.
聊天中有一个问题，
A question from the chat,
你说的字节流是什么意思。
what do you mean by a stream of bytes.
我的意思是如果一个文件包含一些字节，
I I just mean that if a file contains a bunch of bytes,
然后读取连续一百万字节的内容，
then read then successive spilling a pile contains a million bytes,
如果你进行连续的 read 调用，
if you make a sequence of read calls,
每次 100 字节，
each for 100 bytes,
你知道，只会读取第一个 100 字节，
you know I'll just read the first hundred bytes
然后是第二个 100 字节，
and then the second hundred bytes and
然后是第三个 100 字节。
then third, the third hundred bytes,
就是这样。
That's all.
好的，那么这个程序调用 open ，我来运行它，
Alright, so this program, called open, I'll run it for you.
它所做的是创建一个名为 output.txt 的新文件，
What it does is open creates a new file called output.txt,
然后向其中写入一些字节，
and then write some bytes to it,
我已经完成了这个操作，
I'm gonna finish this,
但是我们看不到任何东西，
so we don't see anything,
因为它将数据放到了这个文件中，
because it broke data, this file,
但是我们可以查看它创建的 output.txt 文件，
open, but we can look this output.txt file that created it,
可以看到 ooo 写在那里。
and see the "ooo" wrote there,
程序中的第 11 行调用了 open 系统调用，
so an eleven in the program makes the open system call,
给它一个文件名 output.txt ，
give it a filename output.txt
open 中第二个参数中的 O_ 选项或标志，
and the O underscore stuff in the second argument to open or flags
告诉内核中实现的 open 系统调用，
that tell the open system call implementation in the kernel,
我们想要使用这个名字创建一个文件，并且写入。
that we'd like to create a file with its name and we're going to write it,
open 返回新分配的文件描述符。
open returns a newly allocated file descriptor.
文件描述符只是一个很小的数字，
And the file descriptor is just a small number,
可能是 2 3 或 4 等。
probably two or three or four something.
然后我们将相同的文件描述符与缓冲区一起传递，
And then we pass that same file descriptor right along with the buffer
有多种方式写入数据，
and a number of ways to write that writes data,
对于文件描述符索引用的文件。
the file, the file descriptor refers to.
文件描述符实际上做的是
What that file descriptor is actually doing is
索引到内核中一个维护进程状态的表中，
indexing into a little table inside the kernel maintains state for each process,
就是你运行的每个程序，
that's running each program that you run and among other things,
内核为每个进程记住一张表，
the kernel remembers a table for every running process
（表中）通过文件描述符进行索引，
of index by file descriptors
这张表告诉内核每个文件描述符引用的是什么。
and the table sort of tells the kernel what each file descriptor refers to.
好的，关键点是每个进程
Okay, a critical point is that each process
都有自己的文件描述符空间。
has its own sort of space of file descriptors.
因此，在运行两个不同的进程前，
So, before running two different processes,
两个不同的程序，
two different programs and different processes
它们都会打开一个文件，
and they both open a file,
它们可能会得到相同的文件描述符编号，
they may actually get the same number back as a file descriptor,
但是因为内核为每个进程维护单独的文件描述符，
but because the kernel maintains a separate file descriptor for each process,
所以相同的文件描述符号
The same file descriptor number may refer to
在不同的进程中可能引用不同的文件。
different files in different processes.
关于 open 程序，有什么问题吗？
Any questions that open about this little program.
在聊天中有一个问题，
Now we had a question in the chat,
一个不熟悉 C 语言的人提出的问题，
question from someone not familiar with C,
这些文件和普通的 C 程序有什么不同，
how are these files being described different from normal C programs,
是不是因为我们只使用内核调用，
is it because we're only using kernel calls,
也就是说，我们能不能用 python 打开或写入文件。
i.e couldn't we also open or write a file in python.
我想我不明白的是，
I don't think I understand that,
它是一个 C 程序，打开或写入一个文件。
it's a C program, that's opening and writing a file,
然后继续下去。
that's going to move on.
好的，你可能问的是。
Alright so you might ask what actually happens when.
也许问题是，
Maybe the question is
当使用 C 语言做这件事，
when someone is doing it in C,
除了语法，与使用 python 有什么不同。
any different than doing it in python minus the syntax.
它不是。
Well it's not really, um.
当然也有办法。
And, there's certainly ways to, um.
Python 提供了良好的函数调用，打开文件或做这些事。
Python provides nice function calls for opening and doing all these things too.
打开文件，比如读写文件，
Or opening files, for example in reading writing files,
通常有一个层级比较高的函数，
there's a layer of a higher somewhat higher level functions typically,
比如，没有指向内存的指针。
not pointers the memory, for example.
Python 也为你提供了更多的错误检查，
And python has more error checking for you,
但是当你在 python 中打开文件，
but when you open a file in python
或在 python 中写文件，
or write a file on python,
python 调用底层的系统调用。
the python calls you make boil down to system calls just like these.
这个答案怎么样。
Is that a good answer.
我想是的。
Think so.
好的。
Alright.
我在这里讨论，
I've been over here talking to the,
xv6 是 unix ，比如 shell ，
xv6 is unix, like shell
shell 人们也经常称作命令行接口，
and the shell is what people often call the command line interface,
相对更图形化的用户界面。
as opposed to more graphical user interface.
shell 是，
The shell turns,
如果你没有用过 shell ，
if you haven't used the shell,
shell 是一个非常有用的界面，
the shell turns out to be a pretty useful interface
对于 unix 系统的系统管理，
for things like system management of unix systems,
他提供了很多实用程序，
it provides a lot of utilities
来处理文件，开发程序，
for messing around with files and for program development
以及编写脚本来完成这些事。
and on writing scripts to do all these things.
所以在继续之前。
So, some before run.
我想演示几个 shell 功能，
I just want to demonstrate a few shell features.
当你输入东西的时候，
Ordinarily, when you type things,
你在高数 shell 运行一个程序，
you're telling the shell to run a program,
所以当我输入 ls ，
so when I type ls,
我的意思是要求 shell 运行名为 ls 的程序，
what that means is I'm asking the shell to run the program whose name is ls
这真正的含义是
and what that really means is
在文件系统中，有一个叫做 ls 的文件
there's a file in the file system called ls,
它包含一些指令，一些机器指令，
that contains some instructions, some machine instructions
我要求 shell 运行 ls 文件中的这些指令，
and I'm asking the shell to run the instructions that are in the file called ls,
现在 ls 真正做的是，
ls, now ls what it actually does is,
获取当前目录中的文件列表，
get a listing of the files in the current directory,
你可以在上面的第 4 行看到，
and you can see up there on the fourth line,
同其他文件一起， ls 也是存在的。
that among the other files that ls as exists,
这个列表，
and this list is,
一个叫做 ls 的文件，
a file called ls which is in fact
the file containing the instructions I just ran.
除了运行程序， shell 还为你做了其他事情，
The shell does a few other things for you other than running programs
还允许你重定向 IO ，
allows you to redirect io,
比如，如果我输入 ls > out ，
so for example if I say ls greater than out,
意思是要求 shell 运行 ls 命令，
what that means is asking the shell run the ls command,
但将其输入重定向到名为 out 的文件。
but with its output redirected to the file called out.
我运行 ls ，我们看不到任何输出，
I run ls, we don't see any output,
因为输出都重定向了。
because the output all went out.
现在 out 包含一些数据，
Now, I can, out contains a bunch of data,
我们可以，
we could,
cat 命令读取文件并显示其中的内容，
the cat command reads a file and displays the contents of the file,
我输入 cat out 。
so I say cat out.
可以看到这和 ls 的输出是一样的。
Just going to see now the now this is the same output of ls.
You can also run a command like grep
我给它一个参数 x ， grep x 。
and I can give it an argument x and what grep x.
grep 命令通过模式搜索。
The grep command searches for patterns.
同样的，如果我运行 grep x ，
Again if I run grep x,
它会搜索包含 x 的输入行，
it's gonna search for lines of input to contain x,
我也可以重定向，
I can redirect,
告诉 shell 把 grep 的输入重定向到 out 文件。
tell the shell to redirect its input from the file out.
用来查找保存 ls 结果中的 x 实例。
In order to look for instances of x that saved ls output.
结果是这里有三个文件包含 x 。
It turns out there's three files whose names contain x.
嗯。
Um.
我们花一些时间在 shell 上，
We're going to spend a bunch of time with the shell,
shell 是 unix 的一种最传统和最基本的接口，
its shell is sort of the most traditional and fundamental interface of unix,
因为在 unix 最初开发的时候，
because when unix was first developed,
所有的都是简单的终端接口。
all there was was simple terminal interfaces,
比如我们现在使用的，
like the one we're using
unix 最初的主要用途是分时共享，
and the main use of unix originally was time sharing,
许多人同时登录到一台机器上，
a bunch of people logging into the same machine,
很像 Athena ，使用 shell 交互。
much like Athena and talking to shells.
有一个关于系统调用和编译器的问题，
A question about system calls and the compiler,
编译器如何处理系统调用，
how does the compiler handles system calls,
是由汇编语言
does assembly generated make a procedure call
对操作系统定义的一些代码段做过程调用吗？
to some code segment, defined by the operating system.
有一个特殊的 RISC-V 指令，
There's a special RISC-V instruction,
程序可以调用它将控制权转到到内核，
that a program can call that transfers control under the kernel,
所以当你编写 C 代码，调用系统调用，
so indeed when you write C code that makes the system call,
比如 open write ，
like open and write
实际上是 open 是 C 库中的一个 C 函数，
and technically what actually happens is open is a C function in the C library,
但是这个函数中的指令实际上是及其指令，
but the instructions in that function are really machine instructions,
它不是 open ， open 函数不是一个 C 函数，
it's not open, the open function that we calling isn't a C function,
而是由汇编语言实现，
implemented in assembler
在 RISC-V 中，汇编语言的
and the assembly code consists of
这个特殊指令叫做 ecall ，
this special instructions actually called ecall, on RISC-V,
这个特殊指令转移控制权到内核中，
the special instruction that transfers control into the kernel,
然后内核查看进程内存和寄存器，
and then the kernel looks at the processes memory and registers
找出参数是什么。
to figure out what the arguments were.
好的，下一个例子，我想看的程序是 fork 。
Alright the next example, I want to look at is example program that calls fork.
创建进程，这是很简单的 fork 的应用，
Creating process, so this is the very simple use of fork,
在第 12 行，我们调用了 fork ，
at line twelve we're calling fork
fork 所做的是，
and what fork does is
创建一个调用进程的指令和数据的内存的复制，
creates a copy of the memory of instructions and data of the calling process,
现在我们有两个使用相同内存的进程。
now we have two processes with identical memory.
fork 系统调用在两个进程中都会返回，
Fork the fork system call returns in both processes,
在原始进程中，
in the original process,
fork 返回进程 id ，
the fork system call returns the process id
它是一个大于零的整数，
which is a an integer greater than zero,
原始进程中， fock 返回的是新创建进程的进程 id ，
the original process fork returns the process id of the newly created process
而在新进程中， fock 返回 0 。
and in the newly created process fork returns a zero.
所以即使两个进程有相同的内存，
So we sort of break even though the processes have identical memory,
你也可以通过
you can break the symmetry of
fork 的返回值区分它们。
old versus new process by the return value from fork.
在第 16 行，你可以看到代码检查并判断，
And in line sixteen, you can see code checks and say
如果进程 id 等于 0 ，就是子进程，
if the process id is equal zero must be the child,
肯定是在子进程中运行。
you must now be running in the child.
当然这里有两个进程，
Of course there's two processes,
在另一个进程，调用进程中，
in the other process, in the calling process,
称为父进程，返回的进程 id 大于 0 。
which is usually called the parent, process id is greater than zero.
所以子进程会输出 child ，而父进程会输出 parent 。
So the child will print child and the parent will print parent,
然后它们都会退出。
and then they'll both exit.
我运行 fork ，
So when I run fork,
我们可以得到，它看起来像是乱码。
now here we get, so it may look like garbage.
实际发生的是，
What's actually happening is
在调用 fork 之后，两个进程都会运行，
that after the fork, both of these processes are running,
它们同时运行，
they're both running at the same time
QEMU 为我真正模拟了多核微处理器，
and QEMU is actually emulating a multi core microprocessor for me,
所以实际上它们是几乎是同时运行的，
so they really are running at the very same time,
所以当它们产生输出时，
so when they produce output,
它们产生每个字节，
they're producing each byte of their output
与另一个进程一起，
at the same time as the other process is,
产生输出对应的字节，
producing the corresponding bytes of its output,
所以两个进程的输出是交错的。
so the output of the two processes are interleave.
你可以看到它们都会输出 f ，
You can see that they're both typing f,
它们都会从 fork 返回。
they're both gonna type for return.
所以你可以看到两个 f ，
So you can see the f from both of them,
两个 o ，两个 r ，等等。
in the o both of them and they r both and so on.
其中之一，
One of them,
你可以看到第一行末尾的 0 ，
you can see the zero at the end of that first line is,
子进程会返回 0 。
in the child for return zero.
我猜父进程应该返回 19 ，
I'm guessing that the parent fork return nineteen,
这是子进程的进程 id 19 ，
that is the child's process id nineteen,
在 xv6 中，意味着是系统启动以来
under xv6, that basically means the nineteenth process
创建的第 19 个进程。
that was created since boot.
其中之一，输出 child ，
And then one of them prints child
你可以看到 c h i l d ，
and you can see the c h i l d,
与另一个交互显示，另一个输出 parent 。
interleave with that is the other one print parent.
是的，这是 fork 的一种愚蠢的用法，
So, yeah, this is a silly use of fork,
但是我们可以在这个输出中清楚地看到，
but we can see vividly in this output
它创建了两个进程。
that has created two processes that are.
并且它们都在运行，
And both of them are running for returning
返回的两个进程都在运行，
both processes and they're both running.
但要注意的是一个输出 child ，另一个输出 parent ，
But also note that one printed child and the other parent,
这很重要， fork 返回的两个进程不同。
so it's important that fork returns differently and the two processes.
有一个提问，
Question,
fork 返回的子进程总是和父进程一样，
the child process as a result of fork always identical to the parent process
它们会不一样吗？
or could they be different.
在 xv6 中，是一样的，
In xv6 are identical,
除了 fork 的返回值。
except the return value from fork.
你知道指令是相同的，
You know the instructions are the same,
数据是相同的，栈也是相同的，
that data is the same, the stack is the same,
两个进程
also both processes, the process copies
都有自己不同的地址空间，
and they both have their own separate address spaces,
它们都认为自己的内存从 0 开始，
that is they both have they both think that their memory starts at zero
并向上增长，
and goes on up from there,
但是其实是不同的内存。
but it's different it's different different memory, with the two of them.
在一个更复杂的操作系统中，
In a more sophisticated operating system,
有一些细节，我们并不关心，
there are some details which we definitely don't care about them,
它们可能偶尔导致父进程与子进程不同，
they may occasionally cause parent and child to differ,
但在 xv6 中，除了返回值，都是相同的。
but in xv6, they're the same except the return value.
所以内存是相同的，
So the memory is the same,
另外，文件描述符表是复制的。
in addition the file descriptor table is copied.
所以，如果父进程打开一些文件，
So if the parent had some files open,
子进程也会看到一组相同的文件描述符。
and the child sees the same set of file descriptors.
虽然子进程看到的是
Although the child is seeing them
复制的文件描述符信息表。
in a copy of the table of file descriptor information.
我们随后会看到，这是很重要的，
And so we'll see in a moment, that it's quite important
fork 复制打开的文件描述符表和内存。
that a fork copies the table of open file descriptors as well as the memory.
好的， fork 创建一个新进程，
Okay, so fork creates a new process,
当我们在 shell 中运行东西时，
but when we run stuff in the shell,
shell 实际上创建了一个新进程来运行你输入的命令。
the shell indeed creates a new process to run each command that you type,
但它需要在其中运行命令，
but it needs to actually run the command in it,
所以如果我输入 ls ，
so if I type ls,
我们需要 shell fork 创建一个新进程运行 ls ，
we need to shell forks to create a process to run ls,
但是这个新进程需要一些方法，
but there needs to be some way for that new process
来实际运行 ls 程序中的指令。
actually run the instructions from the ls program.
这些命令下面是 ls ，
Below those instructions from the file called ls
我马上给你们演示一下示例程序。
and the example program, I'm gonna show you in a minute.
使用 echo ，
Uses echo,
echo 是一个很简单的命令，
echo is a very simple command,
只是获取你传递的参数，
just takes whatever arguments you pass to it
然后把它们写到它的输出中。
and writes them to its output.
我准备了一个程序，叫做 exec 。
And I prepared for you a programme called exec.
Which a run, which makes the exec system call,
使用你指定的文件中
which replaces the calling process with the instructions
读取的指令替换调用的进程。
read from a particular file, you specify.
从文件中加载指令，
Loads the instructions from that file
覆盖当前进程，丢弃当前内存，
over the current process and discarding its current memory
然后执行这些指令，
and then starts executing those instructions,
所以 exec 系统调用， exec 在第 12 行，
so the call to exec system call exact on line twelve,
它的效果是，
it's going to have the effect of
操作系统从 echo 文件中加载指令。
the operating system loading the instructions from the file called echo.
在当前进程中，替换当前进程的内存，
In the current process sort of replacing the memory of the current process
然后开始执行那些指令，
and then starting to execute those instructions
并且，你可以传递参数，
and in addition, you can pass arguments command line arguments,
echo exec 允许你传递一组命令行参数。
echo exec allows you to pass an array of command line arguments.
它只是 C 语言中的一组指针，
It was just an array of pointers in C,
第 10 行设置了一组字符指针，
line ten sets up an array of character pointers,
本质上就是字符串，
which are essentially strings
并且将该数组初始化为，
and initialize that array to be,
包含字符串 echo this is echo 。
to contain the strings echo this is echo.
这相当于从命令行运行 echo ，
And that's equivalent to calling running echo command
使用这三个参数。
and with the three arguments,
这是 echo 。
this is echo.
当我运行 exec ，实际上，我看到这个输出 this is echo ，
And so when I run exec, indeed, I see this output, this is echo,
即使我运行 exec 命令，
but even though I ran the exec command exec program,
exec 程序说做的是调用 exec 系统调用，
what the exec program does is calling the exec system call
将其自身替换为 echo ，
to replace itself with echo
所以它实际上就是 echo 程序，
and so it was really the echo program,
产生这个输出。
producing this output.
关于 exec 系统调用，有一点很重要，
And something about the exec system call, that's important for us is that
exec 保留了当前文件描述符表，
it exec preserves the current table of file descriptors,
所以 exec 之前引用的文件描述符 0 1 2 等，
so whatever file descriptor zero one two etc were referred to before exec,
它们在新程序中也引用相同的东西。
they refer to the same thing in this new program,
我们已经加载了新程序的指令。
whose instructions we've loaded.
另一点是，原始的 exec 不会返回，
Another point is that ordinarily exec does not return,
因为 exec 完全替换了当前进程内存，
because exec replaces the current processes memory entirely,
没有什么东西让 exec 返回，
there's nothing for exec to return,
对于 exec ，
to exec you know,
读取文件中的指令，并执行它们，
read the instructions for that file and execute them
就是这样，
and then that's it,
exec 唯一返回的情况是，
the only time exactly returns is
如果发生了一些错误，
if some error occurred
导致操作系统无法为你运行该程序，
that prevented the operating system from running that program for you,
比如，如果程序根本不存在，
so for example if the program doesn't exist at all,
exec 找不到名为 echo 的文件，
exec can't find a file called echo,
exec 将会返回 -1 ，
for example an exec would return negative one,
表示出了一些错误，
signal that something wrong,
它找不到那个文件，
it couldn't couldn't find the file,
通常 exec 不会返回，
so ordinarily exec does not return,
它只在内核不能运行文件时返回。
it only returns if the kernel couldn't actually run the file.
关于 exec ，有什么问题？
Questions about exec?
聊天中的问题是，
The question in the chat is,
argv 中的最后一个 0 是什么作用？
what is the last zero for in argv?
它表示数组的结尾，
It marks the end of the array,
C 是低级别语言，
C is so low level
它没有数组语法，
that there's no the C array scheme,
对于代码，没有方法找出数组的长度，
doesn't have a way for code to find out how long the array is
所以告诉内核，
and so tell the kernel that,
你知道，数组包含 echo this is echo ，没有其他东西，
you know we met at the array contains echo this is echo and nothing more,
我们把 0 放到最后作为最后一个指针，
we put zero was the last strip as the last pointer,
每个在双引号中的字符串实际上是
each of those strings in double quotes is actually
一个指向内存中包含这些直接的指针，
a pointer to some memory that contains those bytes,
数组中的第五个元素指向零值，
that fifth element of the array is a pointer's value is zero,
惯例是值为零的指针
the convention is that a pointer whose value is zero
或所谓的空指针。
or what's called a null pointer,
它表示空。
sort of signifies nothing with it,
所以内核中的代码遍历这个数组，
[], so the code in the kernel has actually walks through this array,
直到找到值为零的元素。
until it finds it element whose value is zero.
好的，
Okay, all right,
这就是一个程序如何替换自己，
so this is how a program can replace itself
使用文件中的另一个程序，
with another program from a file,
但实际上我们在 shell 中运行东西，
but actually when we run stuff in the shell,
比如 echo abc ，或者 ls 或其他，
like echo abc, or ls or anything else,
我们不希望替换掉 shell ，我们没有，
we don't want to replace the shell, we don't have,
shell 只是调用 exec ，
shell just call exec,
因为，那样 echo 会替换掉 shell ，
because, that would replace the shell with the echo command
然后 echo 退出，就全部结束了，
then echo exited, that would be end,
你知道，我们不想用 echo 来替代 shell ，
you know we don't want an echo to replace the shell,
所以 shell 要做的是 fork ，
so the shell actually does is fork,
然后子进程调用 exec ，
and then the child calls exec
这是一个很常见的 unix 惯用程序。
and that's an extremely common unix idiom program instead.
想要运行一个程序，并重新获得控制权，
Want to run a program, but regain control
要做的就是调用 fork ，再让子进程调用 exec 。
what they do is call fork and have the child called exec.
这里有一个简单的例子， forkexec 程序。
So here's a simple example, this forkexec program.
在这个程序中，在第 12 行调用 fork ，
In this program call fork line twelve,
在子程序的第 14 行，调用 exec 。
in the child sort of line fourteen, we call exec much like before.
对于子进程，必须使用 echo 命令替换它自己。
For the child process, has to replace itself with the echo command,
echo 做完这件事，并退出。
echo does this thing and then exits.
对于父进程，重新获得了控制权，
And then the parent process, regains control
因为当 fork 返回时，在父进程中返回一个大于零的值，
because when fork returns, greater than zero value in the parent process,
所以父进程继续执行第十九行，
so the parent process then continues to execute at nineteen
unix 也提供了一个 wait 系统调用，
and unix provides a wait system call,
第 20 行，进程等待 fork 创建的子进程，
line 20 for process to wait for for a child that created with fork,
因为当我在命令行上运行一条命令，
because when I run a command on the command line,
我们希望 shell 等待命令结束，
we want shell to wait for the command to finish
在它重新输出提示符之前，
before it prints the prompt again,
在它输出 $ 符号等待我输入更多之前。
before it prints the dollar sign prompt asking me for more input.
wait 系统调用运行进程
So it's the wait system call
等待它的任何子进程返回，
allows a process to wait for any of its children to return
这个状态参数是退出子进程的一种方式，
and this status argument is that a way for exiting child,
将一个 32 位整数
to communicate one integer 32 bit value
from the exiting child to the waiting parents,
在第 17 行，退出参数是 1 。
on line seventeen that argument to exit that one that's the argument to exit.
操作系统将 1
The operating system passes that one
从退出的子进程传递给第 20 行的 wait ，
from the exiting child to the call to wait line twenty,
所以 &wait[应该是 &status]
so wait the ampersand wait is passing
将状态变量地址传递给内核，
the address of the status variable to the kernel,
内核使用子进程的退出参数填充该地址。
the kernel fills in that address with child's argument to exit.
unix 中的约定是，
And the convention in unix is
如果一个程序成功退出，退出码是零，
that if a program completes successfully exit exits with status zero,
但是它在第 17 行遇到一个问题，
but it has encountered an error at line seventeen,
unix 约定这里应该退出码应该是 1 ，
the unix convention is that you pass one to exit
如果你关心调用进程的退出状态，
and so if you care the calling process
可以查看使用 wait 查看其状态，
can look at the status from wait,
确定子进程是否成功。
decide whether the child completed successfully.
Morris 教授，我有一个问题。
Professor Morris, quick question.
好的。
Yes.
exec 调用在第 15 行，
About the exec call at fifteen,
之前我们提到过，
we mentioned not a bit ago,
exec 会完全被 echo 程序替换，
that exec will completely go into the echo program
而不会返回到 forkexec 。
and not return to forkexec,
所以会运行到第十六、十七行吗？
, so, would ever reach line sixteen and seventeen.
好的，对于这个 exec 代码不合适，
Well, not for this exec code,
因为有一个名为 echo 的程序，
because there happens to be a program called echo,
但是如果我在这里修改代码，
but if I modify that code here,
让我修改一下代码。
let me just modify this code.
好的，那么首先我来运行一下 forkexec ，
Okay so first let me just run forkexec,
它实际上使用这些参数执行 echo ，
it actually does execute echo with those arguments,
我们可以看到输出 this is echo ，
we see the output, this is echo,
我们看到子进程退出表示 echo 成功退出，
and we see the child exited to show that echo exited successfully,
而父进程等待。
and the parent wait for.
让我修改一下代码，
Let me just modify the program for you,
替换 echo ，而是运行一个不存在的命令。
instead of echo going to run some command that doesn't exist,
我们先使用 Ctrl-a x 退出 QEMU ，
actually the exit out of QEMU, with control a x
然后重建所有的东西，重新编译我修改过的程序。
and then rebuild the whole thing in order to re-compile. I modified.
再次运行 forkexec ，
Forkexec now run forkexec back again after modifying it,
这次，因为我们要执行的程序。
and this time because the program we're asking to.
实际上，我们要执行的程序并不存在，
Actually, the program, we're asking to execute doesn't exist,
exec 返回了我们希望它返回的失败的输出，
exec does return we see the exec failed output,
返回 1 ，
and the exit one
你会看到那里的 1 被传回给父进程，
you'll see the one there is communicated back to the parent
表示子进程退出的状态是 1 。
which says the child exited the status one.
所以，当出现错误时， exec 返回到调用函数。
So exec returns back to the calling function when something went wrong.
好的。
Yes.
Okay good.
好的，这里需要注意的是，
Alright, something that's going to note here,
我想你们中许多人已经注意到了。
that actually think many of you already noted is
这是一个常见的习惯用法，
that, it is a common idiom here,
fork 后面跟着子进程里的 exec ，
this fork followed by exec in the child
fork 复制整个父进程可能有点浪费，
and it's potentially a bit wasteful the fork copies the entire parent process,
因为 exec 会丢弃所有复制的内存，
but exec throws away all that copied memory
并将其替换为你运行的文件的内容，
and replaces it with, whatever is in the a file that you're running,
所以如果你担心这种情况，
so you know if you're worried about this kind of stuff,
fork 得到的复制，
the copy implied by the fork,
在某种意义上大部分是浪费的，
is in some sense mostly wasted
因为所有复制的内存都被丢弃并被 exec 替换，
because all that copied memory is just thrown away and replaced by the exec,
这种情况对于大程序更明显，
and this affects actually would be significant for big programs,
如果你有个几 GB 的程序调用 fork ，
if you have a multi gigabyte program that calls fork,
它确实复制了所有的内存，
and it did indeed copy all the memory
可能复制只需要不到一秒钟的时间，
would actually take a fair fraction of a second perhaps to do the copy,
不过这也是个问题。
which could be a problem.
但是在本课程的后面，
But later in the course,
你将实现一些优化，
you'll actually implement some optimization
特别是写入时复制（copy on write） fork ，
in particular something called copy on write fork,
会消除 fork 中几乎所有明显低效的复制，
which will eliminate almost all of the apparent inefficiency of fork copying,
只是使用 exec 丢弃复制。
only to have exec throw away the copy.
它使用了一系列涉及到虚拟内存系统的技巧。
It turns out with a bunch of tricks involving a virtual memory system.
你可以创建一个 fork ，让它懒复制，
You can build a fork, that's lazy about the copy
如果 fork 后面跟着 exec ，则不用复制，
and that doesn't do in the common case of fork immediately followed by exec,
或者你实际上不需要复制，
or you don't actually have to do the copy,
因为子进程不会使用复制的内存。
because the child doesn't actually use most of the memory.
我想你会发现那是一个有趣的实验。
I think you'll find that's a fun and interesting lab.
聊天中有一个问题，
Question from chat,
为什么父进程
why does the parent process parent
在子进程调用 exec 之前等待。
waiting completely before the child calls exec.
嗯，这只是偶然情况。
Yeah, it's just chance.
为什么，你知道观察结果是，
Why is it that you know the observation is that,
你知道，
you know,
父进程输出可能和子进程输出相交错，
it could be that the parents output could be interleaved with the child's output
在我们之前看到的相同区域，使用相同的 fork 示例，
in the same area that we saw before, with similar fork example,
它只是发生，
it just happens not to be
并没有保证这就是输出，
there's no guarantee that this is the output,
我们会看到实际上，
we would see in fact,
我们不会感到惊讶，
we we shouldn't be surprised
即使看到输出是以另一种顺序，或另一种交错，
if we saw the lines of the output in the other order or interleaved.
我怀疑这是怎么回事，这需要一点时间和努力。
I suspect what's going on is that it takes a bit of time and effort.
exec 系统造成了一些开销，
The exec system caused a little bit expensive,
因为它必须加载所有的（指令），
because it has to load all those,
需要访问文件系统和磁盘，
you have to access the file system and access the disk
将名为 echo 的文件内容从磁盘读取到内存中，
and read the contents of a file called echo of the disk into memory,
在分配内存，
after allocating some memory
然后释放旧进程内存之后，
and that even after freeing some memory from the old process,
所以 exec 系统调用中有很多机器指令，
so there's quite a bit of machinery involved in the exec system call,
显然，这需要足够长的时间，
and apparently that takes long enough
父进程才能完成输出，
that the parent can complete producing the output,
在 exec 完成，开始运行 echo 之前。
before the exec is finished and started running echo.
这个解释可以吗？
Does that make sense.
另一个问题是，
Another question,
有没有一种协定子进程可以等待父进程？
is a convention that the child can wait for the parent.
unix 中没有这种方法，
There's not a way unix doesn't have a way for the child,
没有直接的方法，让子进程可以等待父进程。
there's no straightforward way for a child to wait from a parent.
wait 系统调用，
The wait system call,
因为这是唯一可用的机制，
because it's the only mechanism available well,
wait 系统调用会等待值进程。
the wait system call waits for your children.
就是这样。
And that's it.
所以 wait 说做的是，
And so what wait what wait does is,
如果你有子进程的话，
if you have any children,
其中之一退出，就会返回，
and one of them has already exited what does exit, then we will return,
但是如果你没有任何子进程，
but you know if you don't have any children
因为你。
because you are.
因为在这种简单的情况下，
Because in this simple case,
只有父进程，
it was just a parent
如果子进程调用 wait ，
and child if the child called wait,
子进程没有任何子进程，
the child doesn't have any children
在这种情况下，
and in that case,
wait 会直接返回 -1 错误，
wait just returns immediately with a -1 error return,
表示这个进程没有任何子进程。
saying this process doesn't have any children.
无论怎样，简短的回答是，
Anyway, the short answer is
没有一种方法让子进程等待父进程退出。
there's no way for a child to wait for its parent to exit.
另一个问题是，
And another question,
当我们说子进程复制了父进程的所有内存，
when we say the child copies all the memory from the parent process,
我们到底指什么。
what exactly do we refer to by that,
我想子进程会再次定义变量。
I thought the child is going to define the variables again.
当你编译这个，
When you compile this,
你知道，在编译之后，
you know, after compilation,
你的 C 程序只是内存中的一些指令，
your C program, it's just a bunch of instructions in memory
驻留在内存中。
that live in RAM.
所以那些是可以复制的。
And so those can be copied.
因为它们只是内存中的一些字节，
Because they're just bytes living in RAM,
它们可以复制到其他地方。
those can be copied somewhere else.
并且使用适当的技巧，
And with appropriate trick having to do with
设置虚拟内存映射，
setting up a sort of virtual memory mappings
使子进程和父进程映射看起来一样，
and make map things look the same in the child and the parent,
你可以复制父进程的内存到子进程，
you can just copy the parent's memory image to the child
然后执行子进程。
and executing the child.
即使我们看到的是 C 程序，
And even though we're looking at C programs,
你也应该把它们看作一些机器指令，
you should think of them as just a bunch of machine instructions,
就是一些内存的字节，可以复制。
which is bytes in memory that can be copied.
如果一个父进程有多个子进程，
If a parent has multiple children
如果只是等待第一个子进程退出，
would wait just return as soon as the first child finishes
意味着父进程和未完成的子进程
meaning that there could be some more interleaving
with the parent and unfinished children
所以，需要方法来保证所有子进程完成。
with their need to be multiple separate ways to ensure all children finished.
是的，如果你调用 fork 超过一次，
Yes, yeah, if you call fork more than one,
如果进程调用 fork 两次,
if a given process calls fork twice,
那么它需要等待所有子进程，
then it wants to wait for both children
必须调用 wait 两次，
and has to call wait twice,
每次调用 wait 都会在一个子进程退出时返回，
each call to wait will return as soon as one of the children exits,
当 wait 返回时，你不需要知道是哪个子进程退出，
you don't, when wait returns you don't necessarily know which child is exited,
wait 会返回子进程的进程 id ，
the wait returns the child's process id as its return value,
所以在 wait 返回后，你可以区分，
so you can tell after wait returns,
哪一个子进程退出了。
you know which one it was at exit.
最后一个例子，
As a final example,
我想演示一下，
I'd like to show,
这些系统调用如何结合在一起实现 IO 重定向，
how all these facilities combine to implement IO direction,
你记得，
so if you remember,
shell 为我们提供了方便的语法，
the shell provides us with this handy syntax,
我可以输入 echo hello > out ，
I can say echo hello is going out,
这运行 echo 命令和传递给它的参数。
that runs the echo command that argument sending it.
首先，发送它的输出到 out 文件，我们查看一下。
First, that sends its output to the file out and looked out.
或者，
Or yet,
使用 cat ，用 out 文件作为它的输入，
on the cat and with its input connected from the out file,
我们可以看到它保存了 echo 命令的输出。
we can see that saved output from the echo command.
shell 这种设置方式，像下面这样。
The way the shell sets this up, is, as follows.
shell 首先 fork ，像第 13 行这样，
It, the shell first forks like on line 13
然后在子进程中， shell 修改了
and then in the child, the shell changes the way
文件描述符的设置，
the file descriptors are set up,
让子进程的文件描述符 1 ，
so that the child's file descriptor one,
按照惯例，大多数程序使用 1 作为输出。
which by convention most programs used for the output.
shell 将子进程的文件描述符 1
The shell changes the child's file descriptor to one
to refer to this output file,
然后可以执行你需要的命令，
and then run whatever commands you wanted
同时保留了父进程 shell 的文件描述符 1 不变，
and that leaves the parent shell's file descriptor 1 unchanged,
这种 fork 的惯用方法，
so this idiom of forking
在子进程中修改文件描述符，
and in a child changing around the file descriptors,
是 unix 中一种常用方法，
is the usual way in unix,
重定向你运行的命令的输入、输出，
actually redirect input and output for a command that you run,
但是不影响调用程序的输入、输出，
but not affect the input and output for a calling program,
因为我们不想重定向 shell 的输出。
because we don't want to redirect the shell's output.
我们只想重定向子进程的输出。
We only want to redirect the child programs output.
不管怎样，这种方式是我们调用 fork 的常用方式，
Anyway, the way this works we call fork usual way,
第 15 行只会在子进程中执行。
line fifteen only executes in the child.
在第 15 行关闭 1 的原因是，
The reason for the close one on line fifteen is,
我们只是对 echo 命令的输出重定向，
that in this program we're redirecting just the output of the echo command,
所以当我运行 redirect ，
so when I run this redirect,
程序本身不会产生输出，
program produces no output itself,
它运行 echo 并把它的输入定向到 output.txt 文件。
it ran echo with its output directly to output.txt.
所以当我查看 output.txt ，
So when I look at output.txt,
我看到了预期的输出，
I see this expected output,
在第 15 行关闭 1 的原因是，
the reason for the close one on line fifteen,
我们想把输出文件描述符 1
is that we want one as a sort of conventional
指向别的东西，
output file descriptor to refer to something else,
而我们不想，我们有子进程，
it happens so we don't, have a child,
不想使用父进程的文件描述符 1 ，
we don't want to use the father descriptor one
shell 使用它连接控制台,
that the shell had that's connected to the console,
第 16 行的 open 调用一定返回 1 ，
the call to open on line sixteen is guaranteed to return one,
因为 open 的语义是返回
because, the semantics of open are that open returns
没有被当前进程使用的
the lowest file descriptor number
最小的文件描述符编号，
that's not currently in use in the calling process
而我们刚关闭了 1 。
since we just closed one,
并且文件描述符 0 仍然连接到控制台，
and file descriptor zero is still connected to the console,
我的意思是，
I mean，
open 一定会返回 1 。
open is guaranteed to return one.
所以在第 16 行之后，文件描述符 1 连接到这个文件。
So after the line sixteen file descriptor one is connected to this file.
我们只是执行 echo ，
We only exec echo,
echo 输出到文件描述符 1 ，就会写入到这个文件中，
echo just writes its output the file descriptor one
and now go to this file
最酷的是， echo 并不知道发生了什么，
and the cool thing about this is echo had no idea what's going on,
echo 完全不需要知道 IO 重定向，
echo doesn't need to know about IO direction at all,
它只是输出到文件描述符 1 。
it just writes its output, the file descriptor one.
只有 shell 知道 IO 重定向。
Only the shell, knows about IO redirection.
这个例子也展示了
This example also illustrates the sort of kind of
fork 和 exec 之间的巧妙分离，
neatness of the separation between fork and exec,
fork 和 exec 是分开的系统调用，
the fact that fork and exec are separate system calls,
分开的函数
separate functions,
意味着在子进程在有一段时间，
means that there's a period of time in the child,
在它们之间，从子进程返回，
between the fork between them for returns in the child
我们仍然在运行调用程序指令，
and exactly which were still running the calling processes instructions,
调用进程，
so the calling process,
即使这些指令在子进程运行，
even though it's running, those instructions are running in the child,
也是调用进程指令在运行，
it's still the calling processes instructions that are executed
所以调用进程仍然能够改变事情，
and so the calling process is still able to change things
仍然在控制中直到第 19 行。
and still in control up until line nineteen.
这种在 fork 和 exec 之间的间隔，
And this sort of interval between fork and exec,
给了 shell 修改，
gives the shell chance to
change what the file descriptor, refer to, for example.
对 redirect 示例，有什么问题吗？
Any questions about this redirect example.
好的，时间快到了。
Alright, about out of time.
总结一下，
Just wrap up,
我们看了 unix ，
we look at unix,
有许多接口， IO ，进程抽象。
is a bunch of the interfaces, the unix IO, process abstractions.
这里的事情，
Thing to take away from this,
接口相对简单，
is if the interfaces are relatively simple
只是传递一个整数，
and just pass an integer
比如文件描述符和进程 id ，
like file descriptors and process ids,
作为系统调用的参数传递。
back and forth across its arguments system calls.
但是，接口内部函数是相当复杂的，
But, well, the functionality inside the interface is relatively sophisticated,
比如创建进程，复制进程，
like creating new processes and copying the current process
此外，我还展示了一些例子，
and furthermore I show some examples
单独的抽象如何合并在一起使用，
of ways in which the abstractions individually simple combine in useful ways,
比如，产生 IO 重定向。
for example to produce IO redirection.
有一个下周末到期的实验，
There's a lab due at the end of next week
那个实验涉及到编写更多简单使用程序，
and that lab involves writing more simple utilities
就像我在讨论中展示的那样。
like the ones I showed that use the system calls that we discuss.
所以，祝你在实验玩得开心，
So, have fun with that lab
下周上课再见。
and I'll see you in class next week.
就是这些。
And that's it.
谢谢。
Thank you.
既然我是录视频的人，
Since I'm the one recording,
我该怎么结束这个呢，
how do I end this,
第一次在课程中录制。
first time recording in lecture.
它们会自己退出。
They will be exit.
我不用做什么操作，退出，它就会保存到一些地方。
Okay, nothing special I can just exit it will be saved somewhere.
是的。
Yes.
太棒了。
Awesome.
我想会创建一些文件夹并把文件放到里面。
I assume will create some directory and sticking a file in that directory.
这节课之后有办公时间，是吗。
There's also office hours right after this right.
是的。
Yes.
完美。
Perfect.
太酷了。
Cool.
好的。
Alright.
谢谢，下周见，
Thank you and I'll see you next week,
谢谢。
thanks.